the year 2022 which has recently passed
can easily be called the year of neural
networks after all we got a language
model which can write you a surprisingly
decent assay an AI art generator and
even a platform which turns any image
into anime all of this was made possible
by the development of artificial neural
networks a type of computing system
modeled as a network of interconnected
nodes which can learn to solve problems
by recognizing patterns hidden in the
training data and if you go online and
Google artificial neural networks you
are likely to see statements such as
they work pretty much like your brain
well you see such claims although
attractive can be a bit misleading
because biological neurons are actually
much more powerful than it was
previously thought
in this video we will see why individual
neurons in your brain function
essentially like full-blown neural
networks themselves equipped with insane
information processing capabilities as
well as some of the physiological
mechanisms that account for this
computational complexity if you're
interested stay tuned
before we begin I'd like to warn you
that this video is not on artificial
neural networks per se we're not going
to talk about back propagation or
gradient descent or any of that stuff in
detail but we are going to talk about
their relationship with biological
neurons as well as some of the
applications to Modern Neuroscience but
more on that later early neural networks
were indeed inspired by the descriptions
of biological neurons which people
thought to be accurate at the time in
fact the birth of machine learning as we
know it can be traced back to 1943 when
Walter Pitts and Warren McCulloch
introduced the notion of a perceptron
despite the fancy name the idea is quite
simple
the perceptron was created to function
like an individual nerve cell which in
this Doctrine works like a simple
summator and comparator this just means
that it receives the an input set of
numbers multiplies them by some
coefficients also called weights sums
everything together and compares the
result with a threshold if the resulting
value exceeds the threshold the
perceptron sends a number one as an
output to its neighbors
you interconnect a bunch of these
perceptrons with each other such that
the output of one serves as an input to
a downstream perceptron include an input
and output layer and boom you got a
neural network and to train the network
means to somehow adjust the values of
these input weights to make it match an
input to a correct output
but at that point the fields of machine
learning and neurobiology pretty much
Leverage
over the years people have invented a
bunch of activation functions organized
neurons in a multitude of different
network architectures came up with
algorithms to change the weights
efficiently and so much more but because
we still refer to the nodes in such
networks as neurons a lot of people
believe that biological neurons in the
brain function exactly like their
perceptron counterparts the main goal of
this video is to exonerate biological
neurons and show that single cells are
much more computationally powerful and
sophisticated than you might think but
to understand the computational
complexity of a neuron it's helpful to
remind ourselves of the basic biology
behind neural computations if you open
any Neuroscience textbook one of the
first things you'll see is the structure
of a typical neuron usually consisting
of the dendrites Soma or cell body and
in Axon
let's put dendrites aside from now as
they will become key players later on
you probably know the key property of
neurons is that they are electrically
excitable cells which means they have
the capacity to generate brief
electrical pulses that are propagated to
other neurons forming a basis of
communication between cells in
biological systems electric charge is
carried by ions such as sodium potassium
chloride and calcium which are floating
both inside and outside the cells in
different proportions
cells are separated from the outside
world by a lipid membrane a barrier
normally impermeable to ions however
neurons possess special proteins forming
channels through which specific ions can
cross the membrane and which can open
and close through a variety of
mechanisms as we'll see further
so by regulating the flow of ions
through the shells cells can control the
balance of electric charges and thus
control the membrane voltage namely when
positive ions flow into the cell they
are said to depolarize the membrane
increasing the voltage making the
potential more positive and vice versa
for negative ions
from the whole zoo of ion channels we'll
be mostly interested in What's called
the voltage-gated channels which can
open and close depending on the value of
membrane potential
in school we usually learn about
voltage-gated channels in the context of
action potential generation so just to
remind ourselves an action potential
which is the unit of communication is
often said to be all or none output of a
neuron in a simplified description it is
generated at the origin of an axon where
there is a large number of special
sodium channels that open when the
membrane voltage exceeds a certain
threshold because sodium is a positively
charged ion when it rushes into the cell
the membrane gets depolarized even
further recruiting more sodium channels
to open and so forth like a positive
feedback loop that wave of sodium
channels opening up is transmitted along
the axon and gets indirectly passed onto
other neurons by the means of synaptic
transmission however sodium channels
don't stay open forever and eventually
they close well another type of channels
opens allowing potassium also a
positively charged ion to leave the cell
bringing the membrane voltage back to
its resting level
ta-da we have just generated an action
potential and sent one bit of
information to Downstream neurons you
might already see why the initial
description of a neuron as a perceptron
seemed reasonable
after all we have just witnessed how a
thresholding function is implemented in
a neuron through voltage-gated channels
so that part is accurate right indeed
the main problem with the perceptron is
mostly with inputs not the output it
it's time for us to get back to the
dendrites we've been putting off and see
how exactly they contribute to the
computations on incoming information now
the weight is often presented and this
is the way I was taught is that dead
rights function like passive receivers
of information
you see this signal is transmitted
between the two cells when the action of
one neuron forms a special connection a
synapse with a dendrite of another
neuron upon the action potential of a
sender neuron or pre-synaptic cell there
is a chain of chemical reactions which
leads to a release of signal molecules
and eventually resulting in the opening
of neurotransmitter gated ion channels
on the membrane of the receiver
postsynaptic neuron this flux of ions
across the membrane of our postsynaptic
cell leads to its depolarization which
is propagated along the dendritic tree
and the laws of such propagation of
electrical signals in passive membrane
is conventionally described by a cable
Theory
in that Paradigm the dendrites are just
that cables whose only job is to
transmit electrical signals to the Suma
for those of you who are more interested
dendrites are actually treated as
imperfect leaky cables since a single
portion of a dendrite is described as a
patch of lipid membrane with capacitive
properties and a resistive component
corresponding to a leak of ions through
passive permanently open ion channels as
a result the depolarization level is
attenuated as it travels along the
dendrite in other words the function of
dendrites is reduced to summing the
incoming signals where the weight of a
synaptic input is determined by the
amount of receptors and how far away the
synapse is from the cell body
together with the threshold happening at
the Soma this gives us the biological
basis for the perceptron model
however as neuroscientists studied the
cells more closely it became clear that
dendrites are anything but passive
cables and the reason for that is that
apart from permanently open passive ion
channels which give them their leaky
properties dendrites are also covered by
a myriad of voltage-gated ion channels
which equip the dendritic tree with
powerful information processing
capabilities even more powerful than
this Soma itself for example dendrites
actually contain voltage-gated sodium
channels similar to the ones found on
the Axon they allow action potentials to
travel in Reverse Direction and
influence the postsynaptic sites
this is called back propagation and it
plays an important role in synaptic
plasticity adjusting the weights of
inputs fast sodium channels also give
dendrites an ability to generate their
own small action potential like
depolarizations which can transiently
amplify synaptic inputs
another important type of channel is
nmda receptor which requires both
sufficient membrane depolarization and
the presence of neurotransmitter to open
thus functioning like a kind of
coincidence detector
nmda channel is non-selective to cations
allowing both calcium and sodium to flow
into the cells which has great
implications for things like synaptic
plasticity
this depolarizing event is often called
an nmda Spike
unlike pure sodium spikelets these are
generated by the influx of calcium as
well and are characterized by a much
longer time scale of hundreds of
milliseconds importantly to our
discussion nmda channels allow the
dendrites to perform non-linear
integration of incoming information
this equips dendrites with vast
computational complexity for example
dendrites can discriminate the order of
incoming Action potentials this means
that if you took a group of synapses on
a dendrite of a cortical pyramidal
neuron then a sequential activation of
them in one direction will produce a
fundamentally different electrical and
chemical response than activation in
Reverse Direction and this is sensitive
not only to order but also to the
velocity of activation
thus single neurons have a mechanism to
process temporal patterns and generate
sequence selective output
nmd Spikes have also been shown to
enhance stimulus selectivity in the
visual cortex of awake animals
thus contributing to behaviorally
relevant neural computations in the
intact brain if you're interested in
learning more about this paper and the
key result I have a dedicated short clip
available for my patreon supporters
if you would like to support the Channel
vote for video topics and enjoy the
bonus content you can find more
information by following the link in the
description but today I'd like to focus
on something different
what if I told you that certain neurons
in the human cortex are capable of
performing a type of computation that
was previously thought to require a
multi-layered neural network to
implement indeed in 2020 a group of
researchers from the laboratory led by
Matthew larcom published a paper titled
dendritic Action potentials and
computation in human layer 2-3 cortical
neurons where they demonstrated a unique
property of human pyramidal neurons
more specifically they performed
simultaneous recordings of electrical
activity at the cell body and the
dendrite and found a new type of
electrical response that was initiated
at the dendrites by a sufficiently
strong excitatory inputs
this waveform was termed as dendritic
calcium action potential as the name
suggests such electrical events are
caused by the influx of calcium ions but
have a shorter time scale compared to
nmd spikes
remarkably these calcium spikes which
have not been described in other
mammalian species are highly selective
to a particular input strength this
means that if you stimulate a neuron
with too weak of a current the membrane
voltage would stay below the threshold
for opening of calcium channels so no
dendritic spikes would be observed
if however you increase the current too
much no spikes would be observed either
you would need to provide the dendrite
with just the right strength of
stimulation to trigger them this fact
may not seem like a big deal at first
but it's really important for the way we
should treat biological neurons
to better understand what it really
means for the neural computations let's
talk about logical operations
as you probably know the device you're
watching this on stores the information
in bits binary units with only two
possible States zero and one oh and by
the way I will use terms 0 and 1 and
false and true interchangeably
throughout the rest of the video
to perform computations on binary data
computers use what are called bitwise
operations which are like addition and
multiplication but in binary world
they are performing by logic gates which
are the building blocks of all the
digital Hardware individual logic gates
perform simple Boolean operations which
you have probably heard about with the
two most popular ones being and and or
operations
for example the anti gate receives two
inputs and outputs one if and only if
both of the inputs are one
while the or gate outputs one when at
least one of the inputs is equal to one
this is also known as inclusive or
because the output is true when both of
the inputs are true as well
so if we view the inputs as Venn
diagrams the intersection is included
there is another useful operation which
is called exclusive or or xor for short
as the name suggests the xorgate outputs
true when exactly one of the inputs is
true but not both
by the way notice that this agrees with
our everyday interpretation of the word
or
when we say things like would you like a
cup of coffee or tea the word or is
usually understood in the exclusive
sense
and in computers soar can be used for
things like comparing two numbers
importantly to our today's discussion
xor is what's called a linearly
non-separable function
and this simply means that there is no
line for two Dimensions playing for
three dimensions or hyperplane for n
Dimensions that would separate different
classes of output
for example let's consider a perceptron
which receives just two inputs similarly
to the logic gate call them X and Y as
we have discussed earlier all perceptron
does is multiply the inputs by their
weights adds everything and compares the
result with a threshold if we denote the
weights As A and B then the perceptron
essentially solves the inequality ax
plus b y is bigger or equal than
threshold but if you consider the
geometric representation of this
inequality it's easy to see that this is
essentially a line separating the two
halves of the X Y plane
similarly if perceptron had three inputs
this equation would correspond to a
plane cut in the 3D space into two
halves and so forth
that's why a single perceptron can
function as a classifier when two output
classes are located on opposite sides of
that line in other words when they are
linearly separable
returning back to our logic gates the
inputs would be limited to 0 and 1. if
we visualize the and gate it's easy to
see that there is a line separating the
true and false outputs so a perceptron
can act as an and gate
and it is possible to turn it into an or
gate just by lowering the threshold the
xor gate however is different notice
that there is no line that would
separate the zero outputs from the ones
which makes it a linearly non-separable
function
this is why to perform the xor operation
a multi-layered network is required and
it was believed to be true for
biological neurons as well that
individual cells can't compute the xor
function until of course that paper came
out
remember that they described dendritic
spikes showed a prominent cell activity
towards the strength of a stimulus so
for example let's say the neuron has two
sets of synapses A and B
when either one of the two sets is
activated the excitation is large enough
to elicit and dendritic Spike which can
propagate to the Soma and Trigger the
action potential however if both sets of
synapses are activated at the same time
the strength of incoming current exceeds
the optimal value for the dendritic
spike generation and no such event is
observed in other words the dendrite
just performed the xor operation on A
and B inputs how awesome is that for
those of you who are curious about the
biophysical mechanisms of such
sensitivity this largely remains
unresolved however through computer
simulations the authors were able to
show that this property of dendritic
action potentials can be explained by a
combination of known voltage-gated
calcium channels and special potassium
channels that are sensitive to both
voltage and calcium concentration
but if biological neurons are quite
complex computational devices on their
own
how does this fit into the picture of
existing neural networks that were
developed based on oversimplified
assumptions should we just throw
everything away and start fresh well I
think quite the contrary there is a
promising Future For the synthesis of
ideas from Modern neuroscience and deep
learning in particular I would like to
conclude this video by discussing a very
elegant paper titled single cortical
neurons as deep artificial neural
networks
the authors asked an interesting
question can a deep neural network
accurately capture the complex
information processing of single neurons
in our brains and if so how should this
equivalent Network look like to find an
answer they first created a detailed
biophysically realistic model of a
single cortical neuron using a
reconstructed morphology and populating
it with all sorts of differential
equations describing the Dynamics of
membrane voltage opening and closing of
ion channels of different types fluxes
of ions across the membrane and so forth
this detailed spatial model was
bombarded with this set of incoming
inputs and the voltage Trace at the Soma
was recorded as the output
the authors then trained a deep
convolutional neural network with
various number of layers
to see if it could learn the complex
input output relationship of the
biophysical model when the network
receives the identical set of synaptic
inputs
as a result they found that it required
between 5 and 8 layers to accurately
predict output spikes at voltage values
of the detailed model
interestingly removing nmda channels
from the model drastically reduced the
complexity of the equivalent Network
which now could predict the output with
just a single hidden layer this
demonstrates the importance of dendritic
non-linearalities and nmda channels in
particular for equipping neurons with
vast computational complexity and
surprisingly the Deep neural network
that was trained purely on randomly
scattered synaptic inputs was able to
generalize and could Faithfully predict
the output even for spatially clustered
and synchronously activated synapses
that it had never encountered before
so in a way it was able to grasp the
underlying biophysics of the neuron
which was never explicitly specified
so what does this all tell us
first of all this study suggests that
single cortical neurons with their
non-linear dendritic integration
properties are indeed sophisticated
computational units on their own and
this computation is comparable with a
multi-layered convolutional network
which if you think about it is a pretty
mind-blowing thing for a single cell to
do it also offers a practical advantage
to module individual neurons more
efficiently because even the Deep neural
network with eight layers
is 2 000 times faster than running the
detailed model which requires solving a
myriad of partial differential equations
are you interested in learning more
about the topics discussed here such as
neural networks and differential
equations but not sure where to start
well in that case you are definitely
going to love our today's sponsor
brilliant.org
it is a revolutionary educational
platform which allows you to advance in
stem fields in a fun and engaging way
the key feature of brilliant is that you
get to learn by doing through exploring
interactive demonstrations and solving
problems along the way to ensure that
you grasp even the most complicated
Concepts brilliant offers thousands of
lessons of different levels of
difficulty from math and computer
science fundamentals to things like
vector calculus and computational
biology and the new ones are being added
every month for example if you enjoyed
this video then you might be interested
in a course on artificial neural
networks it covers a lot of Concepts
that you have just watched such as the
perception models linear separability
and convolutional networks in more depth
while also diving into more complex
topics like the advanced Network
architectures don't hesitate to try
brilliant and begin growing your
knowledge base in bite-sized chunks just
by indicating 15 minutes a day follow
the link down in the description to get
started for free and the first 200
people to use it will also get 20 off
Brilliance premium annual membership
alright let's recap in this video we
have seen how the presence of
voltage-gated ion channels turns
dendrites from being merely passive
conductors of electricity to active
computational units moreover individual
dendritic branches have the capacity to
perform exclusive or operation on their
inputs a type of computation that was
previously thought to require
multi-layered networks and finally we
have seen how the complex input output
transformations of information inside
biological neurons require a
computational power of a whole
convolutional deep neural network
so hopefully I was able to convince you
that even at level of single cells the
brain is incredibly complex and
fascinating and that next time you hear
statements that individual neurons
essentially function like linear
summaters you will take those claims
with a grain of salt if you liked the
video share it with your friends
subscribe to the channel if you haven't
already and press the like button
stay tuned for more interesting topics
coming up goodbye and thank you for the
interest in the brain
[Music]
okay